Boker Tov בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody.
Today's daf דף daf we will try to be a daf דף
daf ahead so today's daf דף daf will be Daf Lamed דף
ל Daf Lamed and we will pick up on the Mishna משנה,
Mishna, actually the Gemara גמרא Gemara in the middle of the page
on Kaf Tet Amud Bet כט עמוד ב Kaf Tet Amud Bet
with the two dots where it says Ve'im Chibrah Hayotzer ואם חברה
היוצר. Ve'im Chibrah Hayotzer. It's about ten lines down in the wide
lines. And the issue here was is that the Mishna משנה Mishna
says you cannot have like this dripping from eggshell or something like
an eggshell hover over a lamp dripping oil into the lamp or
a separate vessel where the wick runs from the lamp into the
vessel drawing oil and the concern is seems to be that you
will dip your bread into it and take away oil that's designated
for burning and it'll be Rashi רש"י Rashi actually says it'll be
kibu'i כיבוי kibu'i directly, certainly be gram kibu'i גרם כיבוי gram kibu'i
causing something to extinguish before its time and Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda is not concerned about that. And then the mishna משנה
mishna goes on and says Ve'im Chibrah Hayotzer Mitchilah Mutar ואם חברה
היוצר מתחילה מותר. Ve'im Chibrah Hayotzer Mitchilah Mutar. But if however this
was connected from the beginning by the person who fashioned who made
the lamp then it's allowed because then you understand that this is
a part of the lamp and psychologically you're not you wouldn't take
oil from the lamp. It's only because you don't connect the two.
But if you see that it's all one vessel then you understand
you're not to dip your bread into it. So the Gemara גמרא
Gemara says Tana תנא Tana Im Chibrah Besid Bechafis Mutar אם חברה
בסיד ובחרסית מותר. Im Chibrah Besid Bechafis Mutar. That if you, not
the yotzer יוצר, yotzer, not the person who made the lamp, if
you the owner went ahead and connected it using plaster then it's
okay. So even if you just melded it on or welded it
on. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says so Ve'haanan Yotzer Tenan והאנן
יוצר תנן? Ve'haanan Yotzer Tenan? Our mishna משנה mishna doesn't it say
only if it's done by the original manufacturer? So no, Mai Yotzer
Ke'ein Yotzer מאי יוצר כעין יוצר. Mai Yotzer Ke'ein Yotzer. It doesn't
mean it has to be done by the original manufacturer but what
it means is that it has to be similar. It can't just
be an ad hoc type of a thing. You have to really
have made a permanent connection. Okay. So now the Gemara גמרא Gemara
goes on. Tanya תניא Tanya we learned in a Braita ברייתא. Braita.
Amar Rabbi Yehuda אמר רבי יהודה. Amar Rabbi Yehuda. So Rabbi Yehuda
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was the one who doesn't say who says
that this is not an issue to have this dripping into it.
We're not afraid you'll come to draw to take from the oil.
Paam Achat Shavtinu Ba'aliya Beit Nitza Belod פעם אחת שבתינו בעלייה בית
נתזה בלוד. Paam Achat Shavtinu Ba'aliya Beit Nitza Belod. One time we
spent the Shabbos שבת Shabbos is probably what Shavtinu שבתינו Shavtinu means,
spent, could it mean we went to visit but we spent the
Shabbos שבת Shabbos in the Aliya עלייה Aliya of the house of
Nitza in Lod. Now you might remember the Aliya עלייה, Aliya, the
Aliya עלייה Aliya is also where they had the whole discussion about
the Yud Chet Davar י"ח דבר Yud Chet Davar of Hillel V'Shammai
הלל ושמאי Hillel V'Shammai right? They did it in the Aliya עלייה
Aliya in the second story. So I actually was saw in this
book I've been mentioning by the Safrais on the Mishnat Eretz Yisrael
משנת ארץ ישראל Mishnat Eretz Yisrael that they point out that it
does seem that yes Aliya עלייה Aliya was somehow a designated meeting
room at least for the, you know, in the rabbinic world and
that it does become a place where a lot of important like
rabbinic convocations take place. They even say that sometimes it actually becomes
a verb like Alinu עלינו, Alinu, does not, you know, mean that
when we went to this sort of meeting, into this convocation. Anyway
so we spent the Shabbos שבת Shabbos there
or we rested there, we spent the Shabbos שבת Shabbos there. Ve'hevi'u
Lanu Shofar Shebeitzah Umil'uhu Shemen Venikvuhu Vehinichuhu Al Pi Haner והביאו לנו
שופר שביצה ומלאוהו שמן ונקבוהו והניחוהו על פי הנר. Ve'hevi'u Lanu Shofar
Shebeitzah Umil'uhu Shemen Venikvuhu Vehinichuhu Al Pi Haner. So here seems very
much it was Shabbos שבת Shabbos that or Erev Shabbos ערב שבת
Erev Shabbos they brought us this eggshell and we filled it with
oil and we put a hole in the bottom and we put
it on top by the by the lip by the mouth of
the candle so of the lamp so it would drip in and
so we set this whole thing up Erev Shabbos ערב שבת Erev
Shabbos and that's where we were spending the Shabbos שבת Shabbos and
Vehaya Sham Rabbi Tarfon Vezekeinim והיה שם רבי טרפון וזקנים Vehaya Sham
Rabbi Tarfon Vezekeinim and Rabbi Tarfon רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon and the
elders were there Velo Amru Lanu Davar ולא אמרו לנו דבר Velo
Amru Lanu Davar and they didn't say it was a problem so
you see I'm right you see it's okay. So Amru Lo אמרו
לו Amru Lo they said to him, the sages said, Misham Ra'ayah
משם ראיה? Misham Ra'ayah? You want to bring a proof from that?
Shani Beit Nitza Dezrizin Hein שאני בית נתזה דזריזין הן. Shani Beit
Nitza Dezrizin Hein. The house of Nitza is different, they are super
scrupulous, we're not concerned. Now that's all very nice but the problem
is that normally we say Lo Pelug לא פלוג. Lo Pelug. What,
we're going to get to, you know, each person
gets to decide how scrupulous they are and how careful they are
and if you're very careful then this halakha הלכה halakha doesn't apply
to you? So that seems to be you know something that the
Gemara גמרא Gemara normally really resists saying that. Sometimes they'll say Zrizin
Hein זריזין הן Zrizin Hein about a certain generic class like it
said the people when they're working on the Korban Pesach קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, you know, those groups are Zrizin Hein זריזין הן, Zrizin
Hein, or Kohanim BeBeit Hamikdash כהנים בבית המקדש, Kohanim BeBeit Hamikdash, but
to sort of identify oh you you don't have to worry about
this you're careful, that seems of that is a very sort of
unlikely move in the Gemara גמרא Gemara but here that's what the
rabbis are responding. Right? What, sometimes the Gemara גמרא Gemara will say
that about a particular individual. Right but not to say in general,
well if you, you know, if you happen to be a careful
person you're okay. Right right. So that is true it doesn't say
every person gets to decide but but taking it even more than
just classes sometimes we also find with the Rabbi רבי Rabbi so-and-so
he was you know he was allowed. Oh, like גמרא Gemara will
sometimes say like אדם חשוב שאני Adam Chashuv Shani is what you're
saying. Yeah, like an important person is different. But again, it also
depends on what type of a הלכה Halacha we're talking about. Sometimes
we talk about we try to make it a class, like אדם
חשוב Adam Chashuv might be a class, תלמידי חכמים Talmidei Chachamim might
be a class. I don't know, maybe בית נתזה Beis Nitza is
also a class. It's a type of, you know, maybe it's a
type of special justification that applies to individuals who are זריזין zerizin
and therefore a הלכה halacha doesn't apply to them. But there is
sometimes, we actually have it earlier in שבת Shabbat as well, but
I'm just saying that that license to give yourself... that is true,
but even that type of idea is certainly right, even though it
doesn't become a generic, I mean, even though it doesn't become a
license for every individual to decide, but it does that idea of
making individual exceptions runs strongly against the whole type of לא פלוג
lo pelug approach to these גזירות. gezeirot. Anyway, that's what they used
at least to answer that evidence.
Okay,
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. אבין צפוראה, Avin Tzipora'ah, so
this person אבין Avin from צפורי, Tzipori, גרש ספסלא בעלייתא דשיישא. garash
safsala ba-aliyasa de-shaiysha. Here is again an עלייה. aliyah.
He dragged a chair or like a bench in the עלייה, aliyah,
the second story that was made out of marble, לעילא מרבי יצחק
בן אלעזר le-eila me-Rabbi Yitzchak ben Elazar in the presence of רבי
יצחק בן אלעזר. Rabbi Yitzchak ben Elazar. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so
רבי יצחק בן אלעזר Rabbi Yitzchak ben Elazar said, אשתקוקי לך כדי
דאשתיקו ליה חבריא לרבי יהודה, ishtekuki lach kedi de-ishtiku lei chavraya le-Rabbi
Yehuda, if I don't react to you and I'm quiet the same
way the colleagues of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda didn't react when he
set up this whole candle thing on ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, נפק
מיניה חורבא, nafak minei churbah,
a terrible thing will come out of this, people will think that
I'm okay with it. Why shouldn't you be okay with it? It's
a marble floor, you're not going to make a furrow. So no,
גזירה עלייתא דשיישא אטו עלייתא דעלמא, gezeira aliyasa de-shaiysha atu aliyasa de-alma,
sort of like the רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda case. There's nothing intrinsically
wrong with this, but if we allow this case, it'll lead to
a case that is problematic. So in רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, if
we allow that you come to dip your bread in the oil.
Here, if we allow this, then you'll come to drag things in
a you know, in a where you've got like an earthen floor
when you're not on a second story presumably, when you're on the
ground floor, and there it'll be a problem because of making a
furrow. So this seems to be, I should say, rather than giving
an answer that בית נתזה Beis Nitza is different and we make
exceptions for certain people or certain groups of people, here it seems
just to say, no actually the rabbis didn't agree with רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. They were just being too polite to say anything. And
now he's saying, I'm not going to repeat that mistake about being
too polite not to say anything because people will learn out a
wrong הלכה. halacha. So that's a very different answer. Don't take my
silence as acquiescence, and here I've learned that lesson and I'm going
to respond to you so people should not misinterpret and I'm going
to say you're not allowed to do this.
So now that we're on this issue about dragging benches, we will
continue with that for a bit. ריש כנישתא דבצרה, Reish Kenishta de-Batzrah,
the head of the בית כנסת Beis Knesset of בצרה. Batzrah. רש״י
Rashi makes it sound that ריש כנישתא Reish Kenishta is more like
the שמש, shamash, you know the sexton, but it sounds like it's
really the head of the בית כנסת, Beis Knesset, which was what?
Did I skip a line? These actually contradict each other though, right?
What do you mean? Well the first one says
the second one is saying because רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda was silent...
no, because the colleagues were silent, then that led to a big
problem. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda misinterpreted that they were okay with it
and therefore I'm not going to be silent in this case so
people should not misinterpret my silence. So it is different. It's not
like oh, they're שאני shani that they're זריזין. zerizin. It's like you're
right, they should have said something, they were being too polite. So
anyway, it's a different answer than before. Okay, so now the גמרא
Gemara says the ריש כנישתא, Reish Kenishta, the head of the כנסת
kneset of בצרה, Batzrah, of the synagogue in בצרה, Batzrah, גרש ספסלא
לעילא מרבי ירמיה רבה. garash safsala le-eila me-Rabbi Yirmiya Rabba.
He dragged a bench in the presence of רבי ירמיה רבה. Rabbi
Yirmiya Rabba. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiya said
to him,
כמאן הוא עיילת ליה? כרבי שמעון? ke-man hava iyalat lei? ke-Rabbi Shimon?
Like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says, this is the famous debate
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, which I
said half of what we do on שבת Shabbat is dependent on
this debate, that דבר שאינו מתכוין, davar she-eino miskavein, something you're doing
you're not intending, it's a possibility it'll result from your actions. Are
you allowed to do this? Do we say if it winds up
that you made a furrow even though you weren't intending it and
even though it wasn't a necessary outcome, you've been מחלל שבת בשוגג?
mechaleil Shabbos be-shogeg? If we say... that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says, you can't do an action that incidentally might result... an act
of violating שבת Shabbat even though it wasn't intended. If we had
to worry about that, we'd have to constrain our actions on שבת
Shabbat much in a much greater way than we do right now.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's not a problem, as long as
it's not definite and as long as you're not intending it, it's
not a problem. So therefore you can drag this bench in a
yard because it won't necessarily make a furrow. So he said to
him, ah, sounds like you're going like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and
that's why you're dragging this bench. By the way, it makes sense
that the head of the of the כנסת, kneset, of the synagogue,
especially if רש״י Rashi says it's more like the שמש shamash of
the synagogue is dragging benches around, you know, that's what... so anyway.
So he said, אימא דאמר רבי שמעון, eima de-amar Rabbi Shimon, when
did רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say it was allowed? בגדולים, bigdolim, with
big benches, דלא אפשר, de-lo efshar, that you don't have an alternative.
בקטנים, biktanim, small benches that you could just pick them up, מי
אמר? mi amar? Did he really say it? Now why should... why
is it different? I should say first of all that we would
be inclined, I'd be inclined to think big benches would be a
bigger problem because big benches is more likely to make a furrow.
So you have to assume... well I'd say two things. First of
all the idea that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says agrees it's a
problem when it's פסיק רישא, psik reisha, when it's a definite... definite
outcome, that was introduced after רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. That was אביי
ורבא דאמרי תרוייהו, Abaye v'Rava d'amri tarvaihu, אביי Abaye and רבא Rava
said that to qualify רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So that idea that
he agrees when it's a definite outcome was not originally stated. That
being said, some people, obviously if the bench is big enough that
it'll make a furrow, it clearly will be definitely make a furrow,
clearly is a bigger problem. And some people by the way have
the reverse גרסא girsa in the גמרא. Gemara. But our גרסא girsa
in the גמרא, Gemara, and this גמרא Gemara is heavily debated what
the גרסא girsa is, assumes that bigger benches are less of a
problem than smaller benches. Why? Number one, they're bigger, but they're not
so big it'll definitely make a furrow. So why is it less
of a problem? Because you have no option. So why is having
it... because you have to drag it, you can't carry it. Why
is having an option make it worse? So you could say it
two ways. You could say rabbinically having an option makes it worse
because, look, it's true, אינו מתכוין eino miskaven is allowed, but it's
not 100% גלאט כשר. glatt kosher. So if you have an alternative,
you should avoid it. Best to avoid it. Right? So like rabbinically,
we don't like it so much, but you have no choice, we'll
let you do it. There's a better way to say it, which
is not rabbinic, but is to say, look, if you have an
option to carry it and instead you're dragging it, that means a
little bit more, could be interpreted a little bit more, like you're
intending for the outcome, like you don't care that it's going to
make a furrow. So in the sense that, "Oh, I didn't want
it to make a furrow," if you really didn't want it to
make a furrow you would have carried it. Why did you drag
it? Could be that some level you're, you know, you don't care.
You know, so obviously there's a difference. There's one, "I don't care
whether it makes a furrow" as opposed to "I'm trying for it
not to make a furrow." But it could be that when you
have another... when you don't have another option, we could see the
outcome is unrelated to you. נעבעך, Nebach, you didn't have a choice.
You had to move it, you had to drag it. The fact
it made a furrow, it's not your... it's not your action. But
if you had a choice and you're still choosing to drag it,
you have more of a connection, you have more of responsibility to
the... to the outcome that resulted. So that's what the גמרא Gemara
is discussing, whether רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says his position even when
you had a choice. So he was saying you shouldn't have dragged
it, okay, because רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said his position if this
was a small one and you had a choice. So the גמרא
Gemara says,
ופליגי דעולא, u'pligi d'Ula, this argues on עולא, Ula, דאמר עולא, d'amar
Ula, עולא Ula says מחלוקת בקטנים, machlokes b'ketanin, that yes, he agrees
that small ones are... are less... more severe. But he says that's
where they debate. אבל בגדולים דברי
הכל מותר. Aval b'gdolim divrei hakol mutar. But he goes in the
opposite direction, meaning yes, big ones are less of a problem, but
because they're less of a problem, even רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would
say big ones are okay. They're only debating small ones where you
have an option.
מתיב רב יוסף, Mosiv Rav Yosef, רב יוסף Rav Yosef asks on
this. רבי שמעון אומר גורר אדם מטה כסא וספסל ובלבד שלא יתכוין
לעשות חריץ. Rabbi Shimon omer gorer adam mitah kisei v'safsal u'bilvad shelo
yiskaven la'asos charitz. Here's the original teaching of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
A person can drag a bed, a chair, and a bench as
long as you're not intending to make a furrow. קתני גדולים קתני
קטנים, ketani gedolim ketani ketanim, we talked about big things, a bed,
and small things, a chair. And it says that both of them
are okay. קשיא לתרוייהו. Kashya l'tarvaihu. It's a challenge on both approaches,
because one approach said that they're debating... that he would agree that
small things are a problem. The other approach said that even רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda agrees by big things. So the גמרא Gemara says,
עולא מתרץ לטעמיה, Ula metaretz l'taimei, רבי ירמיה רבה מתרץ לטעמיה. Rabbi
Yirmiyah Rabba metaretz l'taimei. They each explain it according to their approach.
עולא מתרץ לטעמיה, Ula metaretz l'taimei, עולא Ula explains according to his
reasoning,
מטה דומיא דכסא. mitah dumiya d'kisei. Yes, we mentioned a bed, but
we meant a bed that's small like a chair, a bed that
really is portable and that you could have carried, and therefore that's
what they debate. But by a big one, everybody would say it's
okay. רבי ירמיה רבה מתרץ לטעמיה, Rabbi Yirmiyah Rabba metaretz l'taimei, רבי
ירמיה Rabbi Yirmiyah explains according to his reasoning, כסא דומיא דמטה. kisei
dumiya d'mitah. That a chair, but it's a chair that's as heavy
as a bed. And therefore you didn't have a choice. And that's
where they debate, but when you have a choice, even רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says it's no good. So which is a little funny
because if they're all talking about one type of thing, then why
did you give three examples? But okay. מתיב רבא, Mosiv Rava, so
רבא Rava asks this: מוכרי כסות מוכרין כדרכן ובלבד שלא יתכוין בחמה
מפני החמה ובגשמים מפני הגשמים. mochrei k'sus mochrin k'darkan u'bilvad shelo yiskaven
bachamah mipnei hachamah u'v'geshamim mipnei hageshamim.
So this idea of whether אינו מתכוין eino miskaven is allowed or
not, the גמרא Gemara assumes it's not just a שבת Shabbos issue.
It could be a שבת Shabbos issue. שבת, Shabbos, we have special
criteria about כוונה. kavanah. It's harder to transgress שבת Shabbos because of
its high demands of כוונה. kavanah. But here the גמרא Gemara says,
you know, this is really a debate by other עבירות aveiros as
well. If you do something and incidentally you're doing an עבירה, aveirah,
is that a problem? Is it your action or not your action?
It's not just a שבת Shabbos question. And here we see this
issue by wearing שעטנז. shatnez. So you are... you go around and
you sell clothes, okay, and some of your clothes let's say have
שעטנז shatnez in it, or, you know,
and you're selling it to non-Jews let's say. So you can go
ahead and sell ובלבד שלא יתכוין, u'bilvad shelo yiskaven, and you can
actually wear these clothes as a way of carrying them around and
transporting them, ובלבד שלא יתכוין בחמה מפני החמה ובגשמים מפני הגשמים, u'bilvad
shelo yiskaven bachamah mipnei hachamah u'v'geshamim mipnei hageshamim,
as long as you're not trying to benefit from it as clothes
are normally benefit... you know, as a normal benefit of clothes, to
give you warmth, to give you protection from the rain, to give
you... you know, to protect you from the heat. So if... So
if you, therefore, if you do derive that type of a benefit,
then you're אינו מתכוון eino mitchaven and it's okay.
והצנועין, ve'hatznuyin, but the real like careful ones מפשילין במקל אחריהם. mafshilin
bemakal achareihem. They have
they don't wear the clothes, they keep it on a pole and
they hold suspended from behind them, they don't want to be wearing
them regardless. Okay, but you see basically this says it's okay as
long as you don't have כוונה. kavana. So גמרא Gemara says והכא
דאפשר למיעבד כצנועין, ve'hacha de'efshar leme'avad ketznuyin,
here you have another option. You don't have to wear it. You
can suspend it on the pole like the צנועין, tznuyin, like the
careful ones. וכי קתני דומי, ve'chi katani dumi, and it's so therefore
it's like the case of small things that can easily be transported.
And therefore we see and even so we see that רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon allows it. וכי לא מתכוון שרי רבי שמעון, ve'chi lo
mitchaven shari Rabbi Shimon, and as long as you don't have כוונה,
kavana, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows it לכתחילה l'chatchila from the outset.
So גמרא Gemara says תיובתא דרבי ירמיה רבא תיובתא. tyufta de'Rabbi Yirmeya
Rabba tyufta. So that is a complete contradiction of רבי ירמיה רבא.
Rabbi Yirmeya Rabba. We see that when רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon allows
it, he allows it even when you have another option. And again,
that's really a critically important point for הלכה למעשה. halacha le'ma'aseh. It
means that even though you can do it another way, as long
as right as long as you are not trying for this outcome
and it's not a definite outcome, it is allowed, and that's like
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says his position even
when there's another option. Now I should mention that it's really the
comparison to שעטנז shatnez is a challenging one, because there, it's a
פסיק רישא, psik reisha, right? According to the way אביי Abaye and
רבא Rava say that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees that when it's
a definite outcome it's a problem, well, by the שעטנז shatnez example,
could very well be a definite outcome. You're not having כוונה, kavana,
very nice, but it's still providing you warmth, it's still shielding you
from the rain, and so on. So רש"י Rashi tries to say,
yes, but it's not somehow considered an act of wearing when you're
not doing it with that כוונה. kavana. Okay, but then that makes
it unique to the definition of wearing and unique to a שעטנז
shatnez issue and not a generic type of a question that could
be applied across the board. So this example by שעטנז shatnez is
hard to fit in to the normal parameters of the debate because
here it's a necessary outcome and even if you explain it, you
wind up explaining it in a local שעטנז shatnez way. Yes. Usually
in a dispute between רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda we פסקן pasken like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, but we don't
here. Is there a reason why רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is? Yes,
I mean, we will see as we continue in
the
גמרות. Gemaras. But yes, right now it's not clear how we פסקן.
pasken. Right, it was somewhat debated, I mean, they were debating what
רבי שמעון's Rabbi Shimon's position was, but it wasn't clear that they
were saying that that's necessarily the universal פסק. psak. Now we move
on to the next משנה. Mishnah. המכבה את הנר מפני שהוא ירא
מפני נכרי ומפני לסטים ומפני רוח רעה מפני החולה שישן פטור. Hamichabeh
et haner mipnei she'hu yarei mipnei nochri u'mipnei listim u'mipnei ruach ra'ah
mipnei hacholeh she'yishan patur.
If you are extinguishing the candle because now we're going from lighting
the candle ערב שבת erev Shabbat to other הלכות halachot about the
candle. So if you are extinguishing a candle because you're afraid that
of the non-Jews, you're afraid that רש"י Rashi says that, you know,
they have a special holiday that involves lights, we mentioned this before,
particularly Zoroastrians, and that you're going to now get into serious trouble
from them, or or you're afraid because of of bandits. Now normally
if you're afraid because of bandits and robbers, you keep the lights
on in the house so that they know that there's somebody in.
But here presumably somehow you don't want them to see that you
are around and then they'll attack you. So it's a little funny.
What, פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh then? So the גמרא Gemara is going
to discuss that. Okay, or because of an evil spirit and somehow
you think that extinguishing the lamp will drive away the evil spirits.
Again, quite funny, normally the גמרא Gemara assumes that evil spirits is
more of a problem when it's dark than when it's light. Anyway,
or a sick person who needs to get their rest, then you're
exempt. So Ari comes in along and says a lot of these
sound like פיקוח נפש pikuach nefesh and it's not just that you're
exempt, it's that it's allowed. So we'll discuss that not obligated even,
we'll discuss it in the גמרא. Gemara. כחס על הנר כחס על
השמן כחס על הפתילה חייב. Ke'chas al haner ke'chas al hashemen ke'chas
al haptilah chayav.
Now forget a special case. You had just extinguishing it why because
you don't want it to burn you want to protect the lamp,
you don't want the fire to singe the lamp, or you just
want to preserve your oil, or you just want to preserve your
wick. In all those cases, you are חייב. chayav. רבי יוסי פוטר
בכולן, Rabbi Yosi poter be'kulan, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi exempts all those
cases,
חוץ מן הפתילה מפני שהוא עושה פחם chutz min haptilah mipnei she'hu
oseh pecham because then you are making it into like charcoal and
singeing it. What does this mean? It means that this is a
debate of we just had a debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon about דבר שאינו מתכוון. davar she'eino mitchaven. The
other big debate about רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon is about מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'einah tzrichah legufah. We
had that quoted earlier in the גמרא. Gemara. Where you are doing
the act and you're intending to do the act, but you are
not intending it for what is seen as the standard purpose of
the act. So you are doing the מלאכה melacha but שאינה צריכה
לגופה she'einah tzrichah legufah not for its intended purpose. How do you
determine its intended purpose? We won't discuss right now. The normal assumption
is is that it's based on what you had in the משכן,
Mishkan, but it's not only that, it's also something that is seen
as a constructive result of the act. So when you extinguish a
fire, what is the type of an example where you would have
a constructive purpose? What are you creating through extinguishing? fire saving things
from burning, but what are you creating? So come, so the only
thing you kind of create is you create charcoal. So if you
extinguish a fire to create charcoal, or to create a singed wick,
like we learned the other day, lighting the wicks before שבת Shabbos
and blowing it out to create a singed wick, then you are
actually creating something. Now, you could argue even there you're not, the
charcoal is already created, you're just preventing it from continuing to burn
and get destroyed, but somehow there it's looked like the extinguishing got
you to this thing of charcoal or a singed wick. If you
are extinguishing for any other purpose, then you are doing an act
of extinguishing but not for its intended or defined purpose. You're yes
you created charcoal, you created this result, but that wasn't your goal,
your goal was just to preserve the oil. Okay, and that's a
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina tzericha legufa. So the first opinion
says in all those cases you're חייב. chayav. That's the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosei seems to be adopting רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon's position and says you know what, all those cases you're
exempt except when you extinguish it to preserve the wick, then you
are actually making charcoal and that your goal is on the wick.
Now again, it sounds like your goal is to preserve the wick,
and we're saying your goal is to create the wick, create a
singed wick, but ignoring that distinction right now, we're saying that is
considered to be for its natural purpose and that's the only example
you are חייב. chayav. First Yoel, then Rivka, yes. It uses the
term פטור patur again, rather than מותר. mutar. Well, that makes sense
because even those that say מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzericha
legufa is exempt, nobody said לכתחילה l'chatchila you're allowed to do a
מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina tzericha legufa. So even where we're
talking about saving yourself some bandages? That was the first half of
the משנה, Mishnah, but we're going to get back to that. But
the פטור patur at the end is precise. Rivka? In terms of
רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosei, let's say you want to put a child
is afraid to go to sleep in the dark, right? You leave
the light on, right? And then
they're getting ready to go to sleep, you can turn off the
light too? Well, again, מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzericha legufa
for him in those cases, you're right, would be exempt, but not
מותר. mutar. Okay, so for him you're not חייב, chayav, but you
are it is rabbinically forbidden. Okay, it's basically doing a מלאכה melacha
on שבת Shabbos with a loophole that you did it for a
different intent. So at least he gives you the loophole, he says
you haven't biblically transgressed, but he does not say it's permissible. Okay,
same for this case which is פטור patur here does mean פטור
אבל אסור. patur aval assur. Let's look now at the גמרא. Gemara.
You will see that there is the גמרא Gemara's page the shape
of the דף daf here on דף ל daf lamed looks quite
different, it's because we're soon going to get into a lot of
אגדתא. Aggadeta. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: מדקתני סיפא
חייב, Mi-dik-tani seifa chayav,
since at the end it says you're חייב chayav if you do
it for the non-intended purpose, like to preserve the oil, right before
you get to רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosei, שמע מינה רבי יהודה היא,
shema mina Rabbi Yehuda hi, you see it's רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
that says a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzericha legufa you
are חייב, chayav, that's the תנא קמא, Tanna Kamma, the סתם stam
voice of the משנה, Mishnah, until you get to רבי יוסי Rabbi
Yosei who disagrees with that. So רישא במאי עסקינן, reisha be-mai askinan,
so in the beginning when you were afraid and it said you're
exempt if you extinguish it, what's the case? אי בחולה שיש בו
סכנה, Ei be-chol she-yesh bo sakana, if it's by a sick person
and there's a danger to life or all the other scenarios in
the משנה Mishnah where a danger to life, מותר מיבעי, mutar mi-ba'ei,
it should say you're allowed to extinguish it or even obligated to
extinguish it. ואי בחולה שאין בו סכנה, Ve-ei be-chol she-ein bo sakana,
and if it's not a danger to life, חייב חטאת מיבעי, chayav
chattas mi-ba'ei, then it should have said
you're obligated a sin offering, right? There's no middle case.
If מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzericha legufa is חייב, chayav,
all these cases of doing it for the sake of the sick
person or for other types of issues are all the only loophole
is מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzericha legufa if it's not
a risk to life. But if it's רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, you
should be חייב. chayav. So either you're חייב chayav or you're obligated.
There's no middle state where you're פטור. patur. פטור Patur only works
for רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon by מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה. melacha she'eina
tzericha legufa. So the גמרא Gemara says you're right. לעולם בחולה שיש
בו סכנה, L'olam be-chol she-yesh bo sakana, all the first cases in
the משנה Mishnah were a danger to life. ובדין הוא דליתני מותר,
U-vedin hu de-lisni mutar, and it should have said not only you're
exempt, it should have said you're allowed and you're obligated. ואיידי דבעי
למתני סיפא חייב, Ve-adai de-ba'ei limsni seifa chayav,
but since the end says that when you don't have those special
cases and you do it for a different purpose you're חייב, chayav,
תנא נמי רישא פטור, tanan nami reisha patur, so it says in
the beginning you're exempt. So you're right, it really should have said
you're מותר mutar to do it, but it was in contrast to
the end where it says you're חייב, chayav, here it says פטור.
patur. So this is a case where פטור patur really means you
are obligated because it's a risk to life. So the גמרא Gemara
says, הא דתני רבי יאשיה, ada tani Rabbi Yoshiya, but wait a
minute, we have a ברייתא braisa that רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya teaches.
אם בשביל החולה שישן לא יכבה, Im bishvil ha-choleh she-yishan lo yechabeh,
if you're concerned about a sick person that they should sleep, you
should not extinguish it. ואם כיבה פטור, Ve-im kiba patur, and if
you extinguished it you're exempt, אבל אסור, aval assur, but it's forbidden.
So clearly רבי יאשיה Rabbi Yoshiya's ברייתא braisa
means פטור patur precisely.
You should not do it, but if you do it you're exempt.
So who does that make sense to? So the גמרא Gemara says
ההיא בחולה שאין בו סכנה רבי שמעון היא. ha-hi be-chol she-ein bo
sakana Rabbi Shimon hi. You're right. We have a middle ground, a
middle ground only works for רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. For רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon you could say you're doing it for its non-intended purpose,
therefore you're exempt, but you're not allowed to. You're biblically exempt but
rabbinically you are not allowed to. So that middle position works for
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and that is רבי אושעיא's Rabbi Oshia ברייתא
braita that the sick person is not a life risk, so you're
not supposed to do it, but if you do it you're exempt
because of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. But the משנה mishna where the
סתם משנה stam mishna is assuming רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that it's
not intended purpose you're חייב, chayav, the only way to explain the
exempt cases in the first case part of the משנה mishna by
the sick person is that it's a risk to life and exempt
does not mean exempt, exempt really means you have transgressed, excuse me,
exempt really means you are allowed and obligated to do it and
exempt there is not precise. So is that clear? Meaning first there's
a question if it's not intended purpose, רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
חייב, chayav, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says exempt but forbidden. You have
a sick person, if it's not a risk to life, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon would repeat: don't do it, but if you do it
you're exempt. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say if you do it
you're חייב. chayav. It's מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she’eina tzricha legufa
and not a risk to life. If it's a risk to life,
then everybody would say
מותר mutar and you're obligated to do it, and that according to
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is the only way to explain the first
half of the משנה mishna and פטור patur is not precise, it
really means מותר. mutar. Yes. And this should apply to any biblical
transgression, not just light. Yes. Okay.
So now that we've got that clear and we're mentioning the idea
of saving a life on שבת Shabbat by extinguishing a lamp, we
have a very interesting little digression in the גמרא. Gemara. Let's take
a look. שאלו שאילה זו לקמיה דרבי תנחום דמן נוי. Sha’alu she’eila
zu l’kamei d’Rabbi Tanchum d’min Noi. So this following question was raised
in the presence of רבי תנחום Rabbi Tanchum from this place of
נוי. Noy. מה לכבות בוצינא דנורא מקמי בישא בשבתא? Ma lechabos botzina
denura mikamei bisha beshabata?
Notice by the way it's much more of a you know of
a the language seems different than the classic Aramaic of the גמרא.
Gemara. It seems to be much more sort of a more of
a vernacular Aramaic, at least that's the way it seems to me.
Anyway, what is the story about extinguishing a lamp, a light of
a lamp, in the presence מקמי בישא mikamei bisha in the presence
of a sick person on שבת? Shabbos? Are you allowed to extinguish
a lamp for the sake of a sick person on שבת? Shabbos?
פתח ואמר. Pasach ve’amar.
He opens and he said, he didn't start with an answer, he
started with an
אגדתא. agadata. אנת שלמה אן חכמתך אן סוכלתנותך? Ant Shlomo an chochmasach
an suchlesanusach? Where is your wisdom? Where is your understanding? So סוכל
suchal can sometimes mean foolishness,
and but here רש״י Rashi says that wouldn't make sense, 'Where is
your foolishness?' But so it could also mean from wisdom like שכל.
sechel. Although the מהרש״א Maharsha says it does mean from סכל sachal
because of the פסוק pasuk in קהלת Kohelles which is והנה ve-hinei
what is the פסוק pasuk about סכלות, sichlus, right, what is it
the
פסוק? pasuk? Anyway, there's a פסוק pasuk about סכלות sichlus in קהלת.
Kohelles. So sort of saying like where is all your wisdom and
your you know talking about nonsense meaning all of your sort of
קהלת Kohelles mentions סכלות sichlus because it's exploring truth and wisdom and
understanding. So anyway, where is all that wisdom, שלמה? Shlomo? לא דייך
שדבריך סותרים דברי דוד אביך. Lo dayach shedvarecha sosrim divrei David avicha.
It's not enough that your words contradict the words of דוד David
your father, אלא שדבריך סותרים זה את זה, ela shedvarecha sosrim ze
es ze, your words contradict one another. דוד אביך אמר, David avicha
amar, your father דוד David said, לא המתים יהללו יה, lo hamaisim
yehallelu Yoh,
that the dead won't praise God. ואתה אמרת, ve’ata amarta, ושבח אני
את המתים שכבר מתו, veshabeach ani es hamaisim shekvar maisu,
I praise the dead that have already died, it's better to be
dead. וחזרת ואמרת, vechazarta ve’amarta,
and you went back and you said, כי לכלב חי הוא טוב
מן האריה המת, ki lechelev chai hu tov min ha’aryeh hamais,
that for a a live dog is better than a dead lion.
So you yourself contradict yourself whether it's better to be alive or
dead. So where is your wisdom? Now it's a very engaging form
of a sermon, right? Like it's not just he starts with the
whole thing, he's like he's challenging שלמה, Shlomo, he's in conversation, 'Where
is your wisdom? You're contradicting yourself! Oh, it's a contradiction.' It's a
great sort of you know should use this device in giving sermons.
But anyway, now this actually is a particular genre of rabbinic literature,
which is actually a particular way in which they would do דרשות.
drashot. And the way they would do דרשות drashot is they would
open with a הלכה halacha question, then put it aside, do a
whole big דרשה, drasha, and then say, 'Oh, by the way, that
הלכה halacha question we asked in the beginning, here's the answer to
it.' And this you find is very common in this work called
שאילתות, Sheiltot, which was edited in the time of the גאונים, Geonim,
but it actually was you know preserves much earlier of these types
of דרשות drashot from the rabbis that again start with הלכה, halacha,
go onto דרש, drash, and come back to הלכה halacha in some
loose way connected to it. You know, it's sort of like we
have preserved that even to some degree today, the whole idea like
a שבת שובה דרשה, Shabbos Shuva drasha, you know, a שבת הגדול
דרשה Shabbos HaGadol drasha is often assumed that the style is that
it has a הלכה halacha component and an אגדתא agadata component. רש״י
Rashi himself refers to a type of a style that they had
in his day. Now it's also interesting that this is רבי תנחום
Rabbi Tanchum because we have a collection of מדרשים midrashim called the
תנחומא Tanchuma or the ילמדנו, Yelamdenu, which are exactly this, that they
start with ילמדנו רבנו, yelamdenu rabbeinu, teach us our master, and it
starts with like a and there's a הלכה halacha question and then
it goes on with a whole דרשה drasha and then it comes
back to the הלכה halacha question and that is a that is
attributed to רבי תנחום, Rabbi Tanchum, the תנחומא, Tanchuma, although that is
seems to have really been like edited and crystallized more in like
the early ראשונים Rishonim period, but nevertheless present, probably presumably preserves earlier
material as well. So here what we have preserved in the גמרא
Gemara is an entire דרשה, drasha, not just like sometimes we just
have like a little piece, but here it's like the whole sermon,
you know, it starts with this question, goes on with this very
engaging style, and then it's going to circle back to that question.
So let's take a look. So it says like this: קשיא, kashya,
you're contradicting yourself. So the גמרא Gemara says: לא קשיא. lo kashya.
הא דקאמר דוד, ha deka'amar David, here, it's not a problem. When
דוד David says ולא המתים יהללו יה, velo hametim yehalelu Yah, the
dead won't praise God, הכי קאמר: hachi ka'amar: לעולם יעסוק אדם בתורה
ובמצוות le'olam ya'asok adam baTorah uvamitzvot קודם שימות, kodem sheyamut, better to
do as much מצוות mitzvot as you can and תורה Torah before
you die, שכיון שמת shekeivan shemet בטל מן התורה, batel min haTorah,
because once you're dead you have no opportunity more to learn תורה
Torah and do מצוות, mitzvot, ומן
המצוות, umin hamitzvot, ואין להקדוש ברוך הוא שבח בו, ve'ein leHakadosh Baruch
Hu shevach bo, there's no praise to God when you're lying in
the ground. So when you do תורה Torah and מצוות mitzvot and
you do God's will, that the action of doing the מצוות mitzvot
is a praise of God. So the dead don't praise God doesn't
just literally mean they don't praise God, but they're no longer doing
actions which serve as a praise to God. When you're alive, that's
when you should sort of that's when your actions will serve as
a praise to God and that's you should seize every moment when
you're alive to do תורה Torah and מצוות. mitzvot. You won't have
that chance when you're dead. So that's the sort of obvious point
why it's better to be alive than dead. והיינו דאמר רבי יוחנן:
vehaynu de'amar Rebbe Yochanan: מאי דכתיב, mai dechtiv, what's meant by the
פסוק pasuk במתים חפשי, bametim chofshi, to the dead have freedom? כיון
שמת אדם keivan shemet adam נעשה חפשי מן התורה, na'asa chofshi min
haTorah, when you're dead that's when you're free from תורה, Torah, but
as long as you're alive then you are not free, but that
actually is not is a responsibility but also an opportunity, ומן המצוות.
umin hamitzvot. ודקאמר שלמה, vedeka'amar Shlomo, when שלמה Shlomo says ושבח אני
את המתים שכבר מתו, veshabeach ani et hametim shekvar metu? I praise
the dead that have already died, what does that mean? How are
the dead better off? שכשחטאו ישראל במדבר, shekeshechat'u Yisrael bamidbar, when the
Jewish people sinned in the desert, עמד משה לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא,
amad Moshe lifnei Hakadosh Baruch Hu, משה Moshe stood before God, ואמר
כמה תפילות ותחנונים לפניו, ve'amar kama tfillot vetachnunim lefanav, and he said
so many prayers and supplications, he prayed for 40 days and 40
nights, ולא נענה, velo ne'ena, he wasn't answered. וכשאמר, ucheshe'amar, when he
finally said זכור לאברהם ליצחק ולישראל עבדיך, zechor le'Avraham leYitzchak uleYisrael avadecha,
remember אברהם, Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, and ישראל, Yisrael, מיד נענה, miyad ne'ena,
he was
immediately answered. ולא יפה אמר שלמה velo yafeh amar Shlomo ושבח אני
את המתים veshabeach ani et hametim שכבר מתו? shekvar metu, I praise
the dead that have already died. Now of course it's a little
funny, it's like were they more answered because they were dead? And
if אברהם, Avraham, יצחק, Yitzchak, and יעקב Ya'akov had been alive משה
Moshe wouldn't have been answered? So רש"י Rashi says what it really
means is if you look at רש"י Rashi he says... where was
he? ושבח את המתים veshabeach et hametim שעסקו בחייהם בתורה ומצוות ומתו
she'asqu bechayeihem baTorah umitzvot umetu ראויים לשבחם אפילו מצדיקים גמורים שגדולים הם
במיתתם מבחייהם. re'uyim leshabcham afilu mitzadikim gmurim shegdolim hem bemitatam mivchayeihem.
So רש"י Rashi says yes actually sometimes we say that once somebody
has already passed away they are greater in their death than when
they're alive. So a little hard to explain what that means, you
know, but it could also mean it's sort of true you know
that some people like you know sort of like artists you know
Picasso had the wonderful blessing of being one of the few artists
that was really recognized while he was still alive, you know, but
a lot of people you know as long as you're alive it's
sort of like אין נביא בעירו, ein navi be'iro, you're underappreciated when
you're actually around and alive and you're taken for granted, and you
know the power that you serve as an example also because people
tend to romanticize and remember things slightly differently you know in the
past than when they are in the present. Anyway there's a certain
power to the people you know to the image to אברהם, Avraham,
יצחק, Yitzchak, and יעקב Ya'akov when they're dead more than that when
they were alive. That's at least at the sort of psychological level.
Here משה Moshe in terms of תפילה tfillah and praying to God,
you know, also there seems to be this idea also of the
זכות zechut and their merit somehow. The מיתה mita of צדיקים tzadikim
is מכפר. mechaper. Not exactly clear you know what exactly what point
the גמרא Gemara is trying to make about that. Just the promise?
What? Just the promise? Yes so the promise that God made that
doesn't have to do with the fact that they're dead. Right. That
משה Moshe is praising them that they're dead more than the you
know praising the dead over those that are alive.
Okay, now it could just be praising past generations compared to this
one. The past generations were greater than the present generation. So it's
not really about dead versus alive, it's about past versus present. Which
is what the point the גמרא Gemara gets to next at least
according to רש"י. Rashi. What I meant was משה Moshe saying that
not because they're dead but because of the promise made. I understand
that but that doesn't fit into the context into the theme here.
Right. So yes. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: דבר אחר,
davar acher, another explanation.
מנהגו של עולם, minhago shel olam, שר בשר ודם sar basar vedam
גוזר גזירה, gozer gzeira, a human officer makes an edict. ספק מקיימין
אותה ספק אין מקיימין אותה, safek mikaymin otah safek ein mikaymin otah,
one doesn't know if people are going to listen to it or
not listen to it. ואם תמצא לומר מקיימין אותה ve'im timtza lomar
mikaymin otah בחייו מקיימין אותה bechayav mikaymin otah במותו אין מקיימין אותה,
bemoto ein mikaymin otah, if people do they only do while he's
alive not after he dies. ואילו משה רבנו ve'ilu Moshe Rabbeinu גזר
כמה גזירות ותיקן כמה gazar kama gzeirot vetiken kama משה *Moshe* made
a number of edicts and תקנות *takanot*, right? The גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
attributes certain things to him like the reading of the תורה Torah
*Torah* that we do in the שול *shul* and so on, וקיימות
הן לעולם ולעולמי עולמים *ve-kayamot hein le-olam u-le-olmei olamim*, and they continue
even after he is dead. And did not שלמה Shlomo *Shlomo* say
well when he said ושבח אני את המתים *ve-shabeach ani et ha-metim*?
Now again, do we keep משה'ס *Moshe's* תקנות *takanot* because he's dead?
And had he been alive we wouldn't have been keeping it? Is
it about by virtue of being dead? So here רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says no, it's not about virtue of being dead. Here it just
means I'm praising past generations more than the present one. The power
of the earlier generations that people are still fulfilling their תקנות *takanot*
and גזירות *gezeirot* is that much greater than sort of the current
generations. Of course, that goes against another פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in קהלת
Kohelet. *Kohelet*, which is, you know, what is it about? אל תאמר
כי הימים הראשונים *al tomar ki ha-yamim ha-rishonim*, you know, were better...
oh, what's the פסוק *pasuk*? Anyway, there's some פסוק *pasuk* in קהלת
Kohelet *Kohelet* about not saying how, oh, the past generations were better
than this generation, כי לא מחכמה שאלת זאת *ki lo me-chochma sha'alta
zot*. Anyway, here that's what's according to רש"י Rashi *Rashi* the גמרא
*Gemara* is at least saying. דבר אחר *davar acher*, another explanation, ושבח
אני *ve-shabeach ani* like רבי יהודה אמר רב *Rabbi Yehuda amar Rav*.
For רב יהודה אמר רב *Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, מאי דכתיב *mai
d'ichtiv*, what's meant by the verse עשה עמי אות לטובה *asei imi
ot le-tova*? דוד Dovid, *David* says, "Do for me a sign for
goodness." ויראו שונאי ויבושו *veyiru son'ai veyeivoshu*, my enemies will see and
they'll be embarrassed. אמר דוד Dovid לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא *amar David
lifnei ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu*, דוד Dovid *David* said to God, ריבונו של
עולם *Ribbono shel Olam*, Master of the Universe, מחול לי על אותו
עוון *mechol li al oto avon*, forgive me for the sin of
בת שבע *Bat Sheva*, right? This was the big sin that was
always sort of the albatross around דוד'ס *David's* neck. Forgive me for
the sin of בת שבע *Bat Sheva*. אמר לו Amar lo, *amar
lo*, God said, מחול לך *machul lach*, fine, I forgive you. Presumably,
there was a lot between the question and the response, but eventually
God said I forgive you. אמר לו *amar lo*, so דוד Dovid
*David* said, עשה עמי אות בחיי *asei imi ot be-chayai*, make a
sign for me in my life that people should see that I've
been forgiven. אמר לו *amar lo*, בחייך איני מודיע *be-chayecha eini modia*,
I'm not going to let people know while you're alive. בחיי שלמה
Shlomo בנך אני מודיע *be-chayei Shlomo bincha ani modia*, in the time
of שלמה Shlomo, *Shlomo* your son then I will let it be
known. And where did this happen? כשבנה שלמה Shlomo's בית המקדש *keshe-bana
Shlomo Beit HaMikdash*, when שלמה Shlomo's *Shlomo* built the בית המקדש *Beit
HaMikdash*, ביקש להכניס ארון לבית קדשי הקדשים *bikesh lehachnis aron le-beit kadshei
ha-kodashim*. He wanted to bring the ארון *aron* into the Holy of
Holies. דבקו שערים זה בזה *davku she'arim zeh ba-zeh*, the gates sealed
against one another and they wouldn't open and let him in. אמר
שלמה עשרים וארבע רננות *amar Shlomo esrim ve-arba renanot*, he said twenty-four
types of praise. If you look in the prayer that שלמה *Shlomo*
made when they established the בית המקדש *Beit HaMikdash*, he uses all
these different words, רנה *rina*, תפילה *tefila*, תחנה *techina*, and all these
different words, twenty-four different types of praise. ולא נענה *ve-lo ne'ena*, he
wasn't answered. פתח ואמר *patach ve-amar*, so he said, quoted a פסוק
*pasuk* from תהילים *Tehillim*, שאו שערים ראשיכם *se'u she'arim rasheichem*, lift up
gates your heads, והנשאו פתחי עולם *ve-hinas'u pitchi olam*, lift up the
gates of the world, ויבוא מלך הכבוד *ve-yavo Melech HaKavod*, let the
king of honor come in. So open up, let me in. רהטו
בתריה למיבלעיה *rahatu batrei le-mivleia*, the gates ran after him to swallow
him up. אמרו מי הוא זה מלך הכבוד *amru mi hu zeh
Melech HaKavod*, who do you think is the king of honor? What,
you? You're the king of honor? We should let you in? אמר
להו *amar lehu*, so he said back to the gates, no, no,
no, השם עזוז וגיבור *Hashem izuz ve-gibbor*, no, no, no, I didn't
mean me, I meant God, I meant the ארון *aron*. Who was
talking about me? Okay, so they stopped trying to destroy him. But
they still weren't opening. חזר ואמר *chazar ve-amar*, he went back and
he said, שאו שערים ראשיכם ושאו פתחי עולם ויבוא מלך הכבוד מי
הוא זה מלך הכבוד השם צבאות הוא מלך הכבוד סלה *se'u she'arim
rasheichem u-se'u pitchi olam ve-yavo Melech HaKavod mi hu zeh Melech HaKavod
Hashem Tzevaot hu Melech HaKavod sela*, open up for God. ולא נענה
*ve-lo ne'ena*, he wasn't answered. They stay stuck together. כיוון שאמר השם
אלוקים אל תשב פני משיחך *keivan she-amar Hashem Elokim al tashev penei
meshichecha*, השם אלוקים *Hashem Elokim* do not turn back the presence of
your anointed one, זכרה לחסדי דוד Dovid עבדך *zochra le-chasdei David avdecha*,
remember the kindness of דוד Dovid. *David* your servant, so he invoked
דוד Dovid, *David*. מיד נענה *miyad ne'ena*, he was immediately answered. באותה
שעה נהפכו פני כל שונאי דוד Dovid כשולי קדירה *be-ota sha'a nehepchu
penei kol son'ei David keshulei kedeira*, at that time all of the
enemies of דוד *David*, their faces turned like the bottom of a
pot, like black like the bottom of a pot. They ashen, you
would say. וידעו כל העם וכל ישראל *ve-yade'u kol ha-am ve-chol Yisrael*,
all the nation knew, שמחל לו הקדוש ברוך הוא לאותו עוון *she-machal
lo ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu le-oto avon*, that God forgave him for that
sin because the gates only opened up for the merit of דוד
*David*, he must have truly been completely righteous or forgiven. ולא יפה
אמר שלמה ve'lo yafeh amar Shlomo, *ve-lo yafeh amar Shlomo*, so wasn't
it good what שלמה *Shlomo* said, ושבח אני את המתים שכבר מתו
*ve-shabeach ani et ha-metim she-kvar metu*, that it's better when he's dead?
Because somehow now, after he is dead, he is, you know, then
people understand that he was forgiven, something that was not given to
him when he was alive. Doesn't exactly explain to us why this
wasn't given to him when he was alive. Maybe he didn't merit
it. The fact that he did that sin, even though he was
forgiven, he perhaps did not merit the satisfaction in his life of
seeing it, of having
everybody acknowledge that. You know, there was still that remnant of the
sin and the fact of the sin, maybe that was something only
that could happen after he was dead. Yes. Two things. דוד המלך
Dovid HaMelech. *David HaMelech* took, moved the ארון *aron* to ירושלים *Yerushalayim*,
but this implies that he didn't put it at his site. No,
there was no קודש קדשים *Kodesh Kodashim*. He had it in the
house of ארנון היבוסי *Arnon Hayevusi*. Right. Okay. Secondly,
we recite that תהילים *Tehillim* all the time in our liturgy. Right.
But we never recite these passages
from... is
more דברי הימים *Divrei HaYamim* and not נביאים *Nevi'im* so it plays
much less of a role in our liturgy. Okay. So now the
גמרא *Gemara* says והיינו דכתיב *V'hainu D'chsiv*, that's what's meant by the
verse, ביום השמיני שלח את העם *Bayom Hashmini Shilach Es Ha'am*, on
the eighth day of the celebrations of the חנוכת המקדש *Chanukas HaMikdash*,
שלמה *Shlomo* sent the people away. ויברכו את המלך *Vayevarchu Es HaMelech*,
they went to their houses, וילכו לאהליהם *Vayelchu L'ohalehem*, and they went
to their tents, שמחים וטובי לב *Smeichim V'tovei Leiv*, happy and of
good heart, על כל הטובה אשר עשה ה' לדוד עבדו *al kol
hatova asher asa Hashem l'David avdo*. So here it was at the
end after שלמה *Shlomo* had built the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash* and
that is, and they rejoiced for all the good that ה' *Hashem*
had done for דוד *David* His servant and for ישראל עמו *Yisrael
Amo* and for ישראל *Yisrael*
His nation. Okay. So therefore you see that it was all in
the merit of דוד *David*. וילכו לאהליהם *Vayelchu L'ohalehem*, they went to
their tents, שמצאו *shematzu*, now we're going to interpret this פסוק *pasuk*
all the ways in which they were blessed. So tents is understood
sort of as their wives, their homes which means where their wives
are, שמצאו נשיהם בטהרה *shematzu n'sheihem b'tahara*. So they went home and
their wives were not נדה *niddah* so they were able to be
with their wives. שמחים *Smeichim*, and they were rejoicing שנהנו מזיו השכינה
*shehenu miziv hashchina*. So that's the more just direct religious they merited
they benefited from the glow of the presence of the Divine Presence.
וטובי לב *V'tovei Leiv*, of good heart, שנתעברו נשיהם שכל אחד ואחד
ילדה זכר *shenisabru n'sheihem shekol echad v'echad yalda zachar*. Back to being
with their wives, that each after they were with their wives and
intimate with their wives then each one of them became pregnant immediately
and gave birth to a male, gave birth to a boy. So
that's a special blessing. על כל הטובה *Al kol hatova*, for all
the goodness אשר עשה ה' לדוד עבדו *asher asa Hashem l'David avdo*.
So what's all the goodness that God had done for דוד *David*?
שמחל לו לאותו עון *Shemachal lo l'oso avon*, forgave דוד *David* for
that sin. ולישראל עמו *Ul'Yisrael amo*, what was the goodness God did
to ישראל *Yisrael*? דמחל להו עון דיום הכיפורים *D'machal lahu avon d'Yom
HaKippurim*, forgave them for יום כיפור *Yom Kippur*. What does that mean?
Because according to the גמרא *Gemara*, the eighth day it actually says
that שלמה *Shlomo* did seven days and seven days, fourteen days,
so when did they begin when did they end anyway according to
גמרא *Gemara* it covered יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* that some of this
rejoicing so they actually ate on יום כיפור *Yom Kippur* when they
did the חנוכת המקדש *Chanukas HaMikdash* but God forgave that, that was
acceptable for that time. ודקאמר שלמה *V'd'kamar Shlomo*, כי לכלב חי *ki
l'kelev chai*,
so that's why the dead are better, yes sometimes the merit of
the dead is better but you've lost your opportunity to do מצוות
mitzvot *mitzvos*. ודקאמר שלמה *V'd'kamar Shlomo* now the third פסוק *pasuk* כי
לכלב חי הוא טוב מן האריה המת ki lekelev chai hu tov
min ha'aryeh hames. *ki l'kelev chai hu tov min ha'aryeh hameis*, a
live dog is better than a dead lion. What does that mean?
I mean you could say sort of what we said before, doing
מצוות *mitzvos*, but then dog, lion, doesn't sort of fit into that.
So כדרב יהודה אמר רב *k'd'Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, like רב יהודה
*Rav Yehuda* said in the name of רב *Rav*. דאמר רב יהודה
אמר רב *D'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav*, מאי דכתיב *mai d'chsiv*, what's
meant by the verse, הודיעני ה' קצי ומדת ימי מה היא אדעה
מה חדל אני *hodieini Hashem kitzi umidas yamai mah hi eida mah
chadel ani*,
God inform me my end and the measure of my days what
it is,
let me know when I am to cease, when I am to
like when I will die. So that's a פסוק *pasuk* in תהילים
*Tehillim*. אמר דוד לפני הקדוש ברוך הוא *Amar David lifnei HaKadosh Baruch
Hu*, דוד *David* said to God, ריבונו של עולם *Ribono Shel Olam*,
Master of the Universe, הודיעני ה' קצי *hodieini Hashem kitzi*, let me
know my end. אמר לו *Amar lo*, גזירה היא לפני שאין מודיעין
קצו של בשר ודם *gzeira hi milfanai she'ein modiin kitzo shel basar
vadam*. No, it's an edict, you don't inform human beings about their
end. So he said alright, מדת ימי מה היא *midas yamai mah
hi*, so tell me the measure of my days. אמר לו *Amar
lo*, גזירה היא לפני שאין מודיעין מדת ימיו של אדם *gzeira hi
milfanai she'ein modiin midas yamam shel adam*. So I don't you don't
also inform people the length of their days. How's the difference between
my end and the length of my days? So רש"י Rashi *Rashi*
says my end means what events are going to occur to me
later in life. The length of my days means how long will
I live. The מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha* has a different explanation. He says
my end means the exact day I'll die. The length of my
days, that we don't tell. The length of my days means okay
at least tell me what season I'll die. That I don't tell
either. Now why not? So the מהרש"א Maharsha *Maharsha* has a nice
little twist. He says the very fact that you don't know when
you're dying means that you know the idea of the גמרא *Gemara*,
every day you should look at like it's the day that you
might die and do תשובה *teshuvah* and don't even phrase it in
terms of תשובה *teshuvah*, you know the fact that you don't know
when you're dying maybe should lead to an idea of like seize
every moment, make the most of every moment. If you know the
day that you'll die, you'll sort of you won't treat every day
with the same preciousness. So if we tell you the day you
won't worry until the last day, even if you know the season
you'll die, three quarters of the year you won't be worried about
how you have to act, you'll only worry during one quarter of
the year. So that's the way the מהרש"א *Maharsha* reads it. רש"י
Rashi *Rashi* just says it's about knowing future events, knowing the day
I'll die. Anyway, so he said okay, ואדעה מה חדל אני *v'eida
mah chadel ani*, so at least let me know this means sort
of like the day of the week that I'll die. אמר לו
*Amar lo*, okay fine, בשבת תמות *b'shabbos tamus*, you'll die on שבת
Shabbos, *Shabbos*. אמות באחד בשבת *Amus b'echad b'shabbos*, he said die on
שבת Shabbos. *Shabbos*? People can't bury me, it's not a good day
to die. Let me die on Sunday. אמר לו *Amar lo*, כבר
הגיע מלכות שלמה בנך *kvar higia malchus Shlomo bincha*, no, by that
שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* will be the time for שלמה *Shlomo* your son
to rule, ואין מלכות נוגעת *v'ein malchus nogaas*
one kingship cannot touch the other even by a hairbreadth, so you
cannot enter into the time that is designated for the time for
שלמה to begin ruling. So he says, אמות בערב שבת, Amus be'erev
Shabbos, fine, so die, let me die at least on Friday, not
on שבת, Shabbos when, you know, people can't be עוסק osek in
my קבורה. kvura. אמר לו, כי טוב יום בחצריך מאלף. ki tov
yom bachatzercha me'alef.
You, דוד, have already said to me, one day, God, in your
courtyard is more valuable than a thousand. What does that mean? טוב
לי יומך אחד שאתה יושב ועוסק בתורה. tov li yomecha echad she'ata
yoshev ve'osek baTorah. I will say back to you, one day that
you דוד will be sitting and learning תורה Torah is greater to
me מאלף עולות שעתיד שלמה בנך להקריב לפני על גבי המזבח. me'alef
olos she'asid Shlomo bincha lehakriv lefanai al gabi hamizbei'ach. More than a
thousand sacrifices. Meaning, so every day is precious, just so you should
be not asking to die a day sooner. Every single day is
more important than, you know, than millions of different things that you
could do, a million sacrifices, every day just sit and learn תורה
Torah, for one extra day. That even every day is precious. It's
a little funny because you're comparing two types of religious activities, right,
you know, so, but anyway. The point is every day of תורה
ומצוות Torah u'mitzvos is a valuable day and should not be sacrificed.
Again, going back to the theme before about better are the living
than the dead and every moment of doing תורה ומצוות. Torah u'mitzvos.
Okay, so he, fine, he's going to die on שבת. Shabbos. So
he took precautions, כל יומא דשבתא, kol yoma deShabsa, I'm sure you've
heard this story before, every שבת Shabbos, הוה יתיב וגריס כולי יומא,
hava yasiv vegaris kulei yoma, he would sit and learn, especially after
God had told him that every day of learning is so precious.
He sat and learned the whole שבת Shabbat in order so that
he would be protected by the learning. ההוא יומא דבעי למינח נפשיה,
Hahu yoma deba'ei leminach nafshia,
the day that he was supposed to die, קם מלאך המות קמיה,
kam malach hamaves kamei, so the angel of death was over him,
ולא יכיל ליה, velo yachil lei, and was not able to find
an opportunity because he was learning every moment. דלא פסיק פומיה מגירסא,
delo pasik pumia migirsa,
his mouth didn't stop learning. אמר מאי אעביד ליה, Amar mai avid
lei, what can I do, what can I do to, I have
to take care of, this is my job.
So הוה ליה בוסתנא אחורי ביתיה, hava lei bustana achorei beisei, דוד
had a garden behind his house.
אתא מלאך המות, Asa malach hamaves, so the angel of death came,
סליק ובחיש באילני. salik u'vachish be'ilanei. He went and he shook the
trees. נפק למיחזי, Nafak lemichzei, so,
he was going out to see, what is all this noise in
the trees? הוה סליק בדרגא, Hava salik bedarga, he was going up
on a step, איפחית דרגא מתותיה, ifchis darga mitusei, the step cracked
underneath him, ואישתיק ונח נפשיה, ve'ishtik venach nafshia, and he, whatever, silence,
whatever, but anyway, he
and he fell and he died. So there, because of that one
moment he stopped learning תורה, Torah so the מלאך המות malach hamaves
got his opening. שלח שלמה לבי מדרשא, Shalach Shlomo le'bei midrasha, now,
that was דוד dead. Now, שלמה sent to the בית מדרש, beis
midrash, he had a שאלה shaila on that שבת. Shabbos He said,
I got two questions. Number one is אבא מית ומוטל בחמה. aba
meis umutal bachama. My father is dead and he's outside, he's outdoors.
So what am I going to do? If he's going to, body's
going to start decomposing, but it's מוקצה. muktzah. What can I do
for my dead father now? And I have, by the way, I've
got another question, והכלבים של בית אבא רעבים, ve'haklavim shel beis aba
re'evim,
מה אעשה. ma e'eseh. And also my father's dogs are hungry, what
can I do? I don't have any prepared dog food for them.
Now it's a little, very disturbing to juxtapose those two questions, what,
what's it suggesting about how to deal with the dogs, anyway, but
it's a little, quite strange, but it's, maybe it's particularly for דרשה
drasha purposes engaging in that way. Let's see how they answered. Yes.
תוספות Tosfos says that he was worried that the dogs would come
and eat his father. Ah, right, so that could be, maybe he's
not suggesting to use his father for that purpose, but that he's
worried. Okay, that's a better explanation. Okay, and my dogs are hungry
and I really got it, so fine, I like that, I really
have to take care of that, you know, because my father is
here, so that has to be addressed immediately as well. It really
happens when people die in their house and they're not found for
a couple days, the pets come and eat them. It really happens,
a coroner will tell you. Right. And especially if the body is
in the sun and decomposing. Right. שלחו ליה, Shalchu lei, so they
sent him, as far as your dogs are concerned, חתוך נבלה והנח
לפני הכלבים. chatoch neveilah vehanach lifnei haklavim.
Take an animal that has died, even if it died on שבת,
Shabbos and chop it up and give them that meat. ואביך, ve'avicha,
as far as your father's concerned, הנח עליו ככר או תינוק וטלטלו.
hanach alav kikar o tinok u'taltelo.
Put on him a bread or an infant and then carry it
because he's מוקצה, muktzah, but if you're carrying it also for the
sake of the infant or the loaf of bread, that's okay. Okay?
ולא יפה אמר שלמה,
so now we see that שלמה said correctly, כי לכלב חי הוא
טוב מן האריה המת. A living dog is better than the dead
lion, דוד being lion, lion kingship, and the house, the dog better.
So there's two ways. One is they answer the dog question before
they answer the question about דוד. Okay, so that was more pressing,
presumably, I don't know. Maybe according to the way Steinsaltz reads it,
you'd better take care of the dogs first before you worry, anyway.
But the other answer, which is what רש"י says, is that for
chopping up the נבלה neveilah for dogs, it could be done even
though נבלה neveilah should be a מוקצה muktzah problem, without some trick.
Moving דוד, who is a corpse, can only be moved with this
trick of putting some type of a loaf of bread on him.
Now that has technical issues to do about מוקצה, muktzah, but nevertheless,
look at what this means, that somehow the dogs are given more
precedence over even the dead body of דוד המלך. Okay, so that's
what, that's. About what that פסוק is referring to. Now by the
way ובעניין שאילתא דשאילנא קדמיכון, U'v'inyan she'ila d'sh'ila kadmeichon, remember that question
we asked in front of you, so רש"י says it's nice that
he sort of puts this in the not you asked me the
question but the question that was asked in front of you, that
suddenly they were asked regarding that question that was asked in front
of you about can you light as put out a candle to
save a soul? נר קרי נשמה נר, Ner k'ri neshama ner, a
candle is called a candle, ונשמתו של אדם קרי נר, v'nishmato shel
adam k'ri ner, and the soul is called a candle. מוטב שתכבה
נר של בשר ודם, Mutav she'tichbe ner shel basar v'dam, better that
the candle of a human being be extinguished מפני נרו של הקדוש
ברוך הוא, mipnei nero shel haKadosh Baruch Hu, rather than the lamp
of God rather than the soul. And רש"י says this is obviously
not the הלכה דרשה halacha drasha about how we know it, but
this is more an אגדתא agadic language, but it still expresses the
הלכה halachic idea. One of the הלכה halachic ideas is right that
וחי בהם ולא שימות בהם, v'chai bahem v'lo she'yamut bahem, that better
to just violate one שבת in order that many שבתות Shabbatot should
be kept. Better to put out one candle of a human candle
in order to preserve the divine candle of light and to let
you know and that is a value that trumps. But obviously this
very beautiful sort of more מדרש midrashic way and obviously it very
much ties into the whole story about שלמה, which the whole running
scene there was about how valuable life is. That even though we
say שבח אני את המתים שכבר מתו, shabe'ach ani et ha'metim she'kevar
metu, still the preciousness of every moment of human life and therefore
clearly that's gonna outweigh the issue about חילול שבת chilul Shabbat and
human life will outweigh. I also by the way do wonder and
this just might be totally my made up that the question began
with the phrase בוצינא דנורא Botzina d'Nura
and it ended with a story about שבת about דוד making שבת
and he went out to the בוסתנא. Bustina.
So I wonder if there's maybe like a little play there on
the words of like the parallel בוצינא Botzina which is the lamp
and בוסתנא Bustina is the whatever you know and there it had
to do with him going out. Okay now we now we continue
with a little more אגדתא. agadata. So let's just go a little
bit further. אמר רב יהודה בריה דרב שמואל בר שילת משמיה דרב
Amar Rav Yehuda brei d'Rav Shmuel bar Shilat mishmei d'Rav ביקשו חכמים
לגנוז ספר קהלת, Bikshu Chachamim lignoz Sefer Kohelet, now that we're talking
about שלמה words contradicting one another we're going to talk about problems
with קהלת. Kohelet The Rabbis wanted to wanted to sort of bury
there's a better word hide whatever anyway the book of קהלת Kohelet
certainly not include it in the cannon מפני שדבריו סותרין זה את
זה, mipnei she'devarav sotrin zeh et zeh, its words contradict one another,
ומפני מה לא גנזוהו, u'mipnei mah lo genazuhu, so why did they
not you know why did they not hide it not sort of
bury
it מפני שתחילתו דברי תורה וסופו דברי תורה, mipnei she'techilato divrei Torah
v'sofo divrei Torah, it's all it opens with the importance of Torah
and ends with the importance of
Torah. תחילתו דברי תורה דכתיב, Techilato divrei Torah d'chtiv, it opens with
Torah because it says מה יתרון לאדם בכל עמלו שיעמול תחת השמש,
Mah yitron l'adam b'chol amalo she'ya'amol tachat ha'shemesh, what value do you
have with all the work you do under the sun? ואמרי דבי
רב ינאי V'amri d'bei Rav Yannai תחת השמש הוא דאין לו, tachat
ha'shemesh hu d'ein lo, under the sun there's no value for your
work הקודם השמש יש לו, ha'kodem ha'shemesh yesh lo, but before the
sun there is. What's before the sun? So רש"י says it means
the תורה Torah which was created before the world was created. So
there in the עמל amal that you do the working that you
do in תורה Torah then there is value in you know that
will stand for you. סופו דברי תורה דכתיב, Sofo divrei Torah d'chtiv,
it ends with the importance of Torah because it says
סוף דבר הכל נשמע את האלהים ירא ואת מצותיו שמור כי זה
כל האדם, Sof davar hakol nishma et ha'Elohim yera v'et mitzvotav shemor
ki zeh kol ha'adam, that what you're supposed to do the at
the bottom line do the מצוות fear God. מאי כי זה כל
האדם, Mai ki zeh kol ha'adam, what does it mean this is
all people? אמר רב אלעזר Amar Rav Elazar כל העולם כולו לא
נברא אלא בשביל זה. kol ha'olam kulo lo nivra ela bishvil zeh.
This is the purpose of creation in order to do תורה Torah.
in order to do תורה ומצוות. Torah u'mitzvot. רב אבא בר כהנא
אמר Rav Abba bar Kahana amar שקול זה כנגד כל העולם כולו,
shakul zeh k'neged kol ha'olam kulo, the value of this is equal
to the value of the whole world is slightly different nuance. שמעון
בן עזאי אומר Shimon ben Azzai omer ואמרי לה v'amri lah שמעון
בן זומא אומר Shimon ben Zoma omer לא נברא כל העולם אלא
לצוות לזה. lo nivra kol ha'olam ela l'tzvot la'zeh. The whole world
was created to be a accompaniment for the people that learn תורה.
Torah Right this we mentioned this once before we had אגדתא agadata
that sort of suggested this in ברכות Berachot everything is made for
me that all of the whole rest of the world is in
order that for the for the sake of the few people who
are going to be learning תורה Torah that they should be there
to provide for him and be an accompaniment for them and so
on. Anyway but because it opened with תורה Torah and ended with
תורה it was going to be preserved and we had to reconcile
it. Now the מהרש"א makes the important point which is remember when
we talked about the עלייה aliyah of בית נדזא Beit Nudza of
who is it below
of someone בן גוריון ben Guryon בן גורות, ben Gorot, right where
they did the יוחס טבא, Yuchas Taba, it said that he wanted
to preserve ספר יחזקאל. Sefer Yechezkel. Okay and he had to reconcile
it. So there we can justify why ספר יחזקאל Sefer Yechezkel was
worth preserving. Obviously it was worth preserving. They just had to חנניה
בן חזקיה בן גורון. Chananya ben Chizkiya ben Goron. So here why
do you have to justify why the book of קהלת was worth
preserving? So the מהרש"א says because ספר יחזקאל Sefer Yechezkel is נבואה.
nevuah. If it's נבואה nevuah of course you have to preserve it.
You have to reconcile it but you have to preserve it. קהלת
is a ספר חכמה, sefer chochma, it's שלמה wisdom, it's not נבואה
nevuah and actually there's a genre called wisdom literature and we're going
to see the גמרא is going to say tomorrow the same thing
about משלי Mishlei that they first They first they decided it was
worth preserving. Once they decided it was worth preserving, then they had
to deal with the problems. So here he says, you first had
to make that decision it was worth preserving, something you didn't have
to sort of determine by יחזקאל. Yechezkel. There it was taken for
granted. But here you had to make that decision, and we will
continue tomorrow to see what the contradictions were and how they resolved
them.